A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Program, Office Files of Gary G. Sick FA1520
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Program, Office Files of Gary G. Sick
1982-1987
Rockefeller Archive Center
Sick, Gary, 1935-
Ford Foundation
FA1520
1.5 Cubic Feet 4 boxes (4 letter document containers)
Biographical / Historical
Gary G. Sick was responsible for programs relating to foreign policy at the Ford Foundation from 1982-1987. Prior to joining the Foundation, he served in the U.S. government as a naval captain and in policy positions in the National Security Council and the Department of Defense. During his five years at the National Security Council, he served Presidents Ford, Carter, and Reagan on issues related to the Middle East. He was the principal White House aide for Iranian affairs during the Iranian Revolution and subsequent hostage crisis. From 1973-1976 he served in the Office of the Assistant Secretary of Defense (International Security Affairs), with special responsibility for security policy involving the Persian Gulf and Indian Ocean areas. Dr. Sick holds a Ph.D. degree from in political science from Columbia University, and his professional experience includes posts in the Persian Gulf, Morocco, Italy, and Egypt. He received his undergraduate degree in French literature from Kansas University where he was the recipient of Fulbright and Rotary fellowships for graduate studies in France. Dr. Sick is the executive director of the Gulf/2000 Project at Columbia University (1993–present), which has published five books and numbers many of the leading scholars on the Persian Gulf among its global membership. He is an adjunct professor of International Affairs and a senior research scholar at Columbia's School of International and Public Affairs. He is emeritus member of the board of directors of Human Rights Watch, and serves as founding chair of the Advisory Committee of Human Rights Watch/Middle East.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of Dr. Gary Sick's correspondence with grantees regarding ongoing grants, grant rejection and acceptance letters, and requests for further information on proposed projects. The collection also contains Dr. Sick's inter-office memos with Ford Foundation International Affairs program staff regarding grantmaking decisions, Recommended Grant Action forms (RGAs), trip and conference summaries, Dr. Sick's publications, and discussions of how to evenly allocate funding to underserved areas of study.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2019:032.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into one series:
1. Chronological Files, 1982-1987
Ford Foundation; International affairs
- Chronological Files, 1982-1987; 1
  Arrangement
  Correspondence within folders is typically ordered in reverse chronological order
  - Chrons, 1982 October-December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chrons, 1982 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chrons, 1983 January-March (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chrons, 1983 April-June (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chrons, 1983 July-September (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chrons, 1983 October-December (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chrons, 1984 January-March (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chrons, 1984 April-June (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Chrons, 1984 July-September (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chrons, 1984 October-December (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chrons, 1986 October-December (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Chrons, 1987 January-February (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
  - Chrons, 1987 March-June (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
  - Chrons, 1987 June-September (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Chrons, 1987 October-December (Box 4, Folder 18)